Guide to the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. records M0750
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
- Record Group 5. Advocacy, circa 1967-1998
  - Series 3. Litigation
    - Martinez v. Jeannette, depositions; includes the deposition of Susan Jeannette and Pedro Martinez, exhibits, and other deponents' testimony (8 folders), circa 1990-1991 (Box 185)
    - Martinez v. Jeannette, reporters' transcripts; also includes partial transcript of appeals, and reporters' declarations regarding deponents' failure to appear (10 folders), circa 1990-1991 (Box 184)
    - Mixed case files; includes Knight v. CRLA, Knight v. California, Flores v. El Centro School District, and Sayler Appellate brief memos (5 folders), circa 1977, 1989-1991 (Box 295)
    - Mixed case files; includes UFW v. INS (sealed deposition and exhibits); Stephen Rosenbaum immigration cases material; ARC v. Department of Developmental Disabilities; Seabolt v. Rossi (5 folders), circa 1976-1987 (Box 388)
      Closed until 2062
    - Mixed case files; includes Tomakin v. U.S., Rosaz v. City of Stockton, Hart v. County of Riverside, Patricak v. Tennessee Department of Public Welfare, Larson v. Romney, and Findrilakis v. Secretary of HUD; documents includes pleadings, research, and notes (23 folders) (Carton 105)
    - Mixed case files; includes material on Chavez v. Superior Farming Company, DBAC v. Alameda County, UFW v. INS, Andrews v. ALRB, Hernandez v. SUSD, Lopez v. Mathews, Mel Smith Chevrolet v. Hernandez, Sebastian v. J. C. Penney, and various insurance cases (12 folders) (Carton 207)
    - Mixed case files; includes Alice v. State Department of Social Welfare, AMAE v. Saxon, and Kievlan v. Maier; documents include pleadings, notes, and correpsondence (20 folders) (Carton 107)
    - Mixed case files; includes COMA v. City Council and Findrilakis v. Secretary of HUD; documents include pleadings, depositions, notes, discovery, research, and correspondence (19 folders) (Carton 106)
    - Mixed case files; includes pleadings, research, drafts, depositions, and correspondence related to Flores v. El Centro School District, research and transcripts relating to amici briefs for Bakke v. UC Regents, and correspondence and research relating to attorneys' fees (23 folders) (Carton 109)
    - Mixed case files; includes material on Maria P. v Riles, Carrillo v. Ballin, Cruz v. CRLA, and Flores v. El Centro School District, as well as declarations for an unidentified 1973 court case, docket sheets from 1977, caseload statistics for 1978, and case handling manual revisions (Carton 266, Folders 1-16)
    - Mixed material; includes memos, reports, articles, and pleadings on topics such as housing and rent, the Stockton CRLA office, and writs of habeus corpus (7 folders), 1974, 1977, 1983-86 (Box 208)
    - Monthly case summary reports; includes reports from various regional offices (9 folders), 1974 (Box 192)
      Closed until 2049
    - Private Law Corporations; includes correspondence and billing information related to CRLA's contracts with private law firms to handle pro bono cases, 1982-1987 (Boxes 200-201)
    - PT&T case; includes proceedings related to applications brought by The Pacific Telephone and Telegraph company before the Public Utilities Commission of the State of California to increase rates, and investigations by the Commission into fees charged by telephone companies in California (12 folders), 1981, 1983 (Carton 149)
    - PT&T case; includes testimony, exhibits, motions, decisions, correspondence, and miscellaneous documents related to application for rate increase (24 folders), circa 1980-1982 (Carton 47)
    - PT&T case; includes Public Advocates, Inc. materials, bilingual services, affirmative action files, briefs, decisions (11 folders), circa 1980-1982 (Box 48)
    - Reclamation case materials; includes clippings, articles, correspondence, testimony, related briefs, grant proposal and reports (8 folders), 1976-1980 (Box 194)
    - Research material; includes material on Medi-Cal, welfare, rural health services, United Farm Workers, migrant housing, reapportionment, reclamation laws, and farmworker disability (13 folders), 1974-75, 1979-81, 1983 (Box 129)
    - Research material; includes clippings from the Food, Agriculture, and Rural Affairs Information Service (10 folders), circa 1975-1980 (Carton 132)
    - Research material; includes news clippings and articles on such topics as welfare, socialized medicine, and agricultural mechanization (8 folders), 1967, 1970, 1973, 1980-81 (Box 230)
    - Schmidt v. Superior Court (Valley Mobile Park Investments), pleadings; also includes notes and research, correspondence, and amicus briefs (10 folders), circa 1985 - 1990 (Carton 294)
    - Stanislaus County Bar Association v. CRLA; includes correspondence, petitions, evidence, and other materials related to the Stanislaus County Bar Association's efforts to keep CRLA from practicing law in California (6 folders), 1966-1968 (Box 76)
    - United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS), transcripts; includes reporters' transcripts of trial and proceedings of evidentiary hearing (4 folders) (Box 187)
    - United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS); includes correspondence, mostly regarding monitoring reports and press releases (6 folders), 1987-1994 (Box 189)
    - United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS), depositions (11 folders), 1987-1989 (Box 210)
    - United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS); includes pleadings, motions and orders (14 folders) (Carton 211)
    - United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS), exhibits; includes plaintiffs' first, second, third, and fourth partial sets of exhibits, various defendants' exhibits, and other exhibits presented during the proceedings as well as subpoenas and SAW records (10 folders) (Box 212)
    - United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS), research and publicity files; also includes miscellaneous data reports and notes on the case (5 folders) (Box 213)
    - United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS), declarations; includes notes and correspondence related to the declarations, applications for temporary resident status (INS forms), and record of proceeding request forms (6 folders) (Box 188)
      Closed Until 2060
    - Utility company employment practices and bilingual services; includes proceedings related to applications brought before the Public Utilities Commission of the State of California concerning employment discrimination by telephone companies, and the need to require telephone companies to provide bilingual services (4 folders), 1981-1984 (Box 150)
    - Western Land Office Inc. v. Cervantes and Hernandez v. Brock; includes proceedings, notes, correspondence, and other materials (7 folders) (Box 353)
    - Zambrano v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS); includes appeal information, motions, orders, excerpts of record, declarations, tarnscripts, proceedings, briefs, appellate rules and procedures, federal litigation procedure, client information packets, statistics, related cases, correspondence, memos, notes (24 folders), 1986-1993 (Carton 228)
    - Zambrano v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS); includes research, related cases, press releases, news articles, correspondence, memos, notes (7 folders), 1986-1993 (Box 229)
    - Zermeno v. PG&E (Pacific Gas and Electric); includes research, correspondence, related legislation, pleadings, and notes (47 folders), circa 1979 (Carton 298)
- Record Group 6. Program files, circa 1970-1997
  This record group contains correspondence, memos, reports, subject files, and other material related to CRLA programs, units (i.e. migrant units), and task forces, as well as its annual Priorities Conferences and related programs and meetings. Task force topics include migrant labor, immigration, jobs, housing, education, land reclamation, and prisons, among others. This series also includes material related to CRLA's involvement with the Cooperative Legal Services Center (CLSC). Also included are attorney and staff training and orientation files.
  - Series 1. Cooperative Legal Services Center (CLSC)
    - Cooperative Legal Services Center (CLSC); includes correspondence, memos, contact lists, dockets, and statistics relating to CLSC; topics include the defunding of CLSC because of cuts to CLRA's funding in the late 1970s (21 folders), 1974-1978 (Carton 62)
    - Cooperative Legal Services Center (CLSC); includes correspondence and memos related to the day-to-day running of the CLSC, as well as the 1977 Legal Services Corporation evaluation of the program (27 folders), 1975-1977 (Carton 171)
    - Cooperative Legal Services Center (CLSC); includes memos to offices, material for back up centers, and dockets (6 folders), 1972-1977 (Box 172)
  - Series 2. Priorities Conferences and Task Forces
    - Priorities conferences and task forces; includes memos, correspondence, reports, and other material on the Asilomar Priorities Conferences and the civil rights, economic development, employment, farm labor, job creation, and migrant unit task forces (23 folders), 1974-1980, 1982, 1983, 1986 (Carton 128)
    - Priorities Conferences; includes memos, correspondence, reports, and conference material related to preparations for the 1985 and 1997 priorities conferences at Asilomar (8 folders), 1985, 1997 (Box 346)
    - Task forces; includes memos, correspondence, reports, and other material on the Senior Citizens Law Program, the Food Law Center, and the Housing task force, as well as general information on CRLA task forces (9 folders), 1974-1977 (Box 79)
    - Task forces; includes memos, correspondence, reports, and other material on the education, housing, labor, and health task forces (19 folders), 1979-1980 (Carton 115)
    - Task forces; includes memos, correspondence, and other material related to task forces on topics such as migrant workers, reclamation, education, housing, and job creation (16 folders), 1975, 1977-79 (Box 231)
    - Task forces and Priorities Conferences; includes memos, correspondence, agendas, and other material relating to priorities conferences in the 1970s and early 1980s as well as the farm labor and immigration task forces (10 folders), 1976-1979, 1983, 1984, 1987, 1990-1991 (Box 232)
    - Task forces and Priorities Conferences; includes correspondence, memos, notes, reports, and other material relating to priorities conferences in the late 1970s and early 1980s, migrant units, and the labor task force (12 folders), 1979-1980, 1982, 1987 (Box 267)
  - Series 3. Sacramento Migrant Unit
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes correspondence, memos, notes, and other materials relating to topics such as education, farm labor, rural health, pesticides, housing, industrial relations, and vacancies on the University of California Board of Regents (34 folders), 1978-1981 (Carton 286)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes correspondence, memos, notes and other materials relating to topics such as children, women's health, state budget concerns, Freedom of Information Act litigation, farm labor, rural health, and clerical unions (28 folders), 1978-1981 (Carton 288)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes correspondence, memos, and other material relating to litigation, lobbying, conferences, and organizations including the Commission on the Status of Women, La Cooperativa, and La Raza Legal Alliance (20 folders), 1978-1981 (Box 305)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes reports, notes, correspondence, and memos on topics relating to migrant farm workers, such as health, immigration, and welfare (36 folders), 1978-1981 (Box 306)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes reports, notes, correspondence, memos, newsletters and other materials on topics relating to migrant farm workers from organizations such as the General Accounting Office, the National Immigration Law Center, and the California Employment Development Department, 1985-1995 (Boxes 307-308)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes reports, notes, correspondence, and memos on topics relating to migrant farm workers, such as health, housing, education, unemployment insurance, and mechanization (16 folders), 1978-1981 (Carton 309)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes reports and other publications on topics relating to migrant farm workers, including family health, unemployment insurance, office of migrant services regulations, retraining efforts for cannery workers, and education inequality (37 folders), 1978-1981 (Box 340)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit; includes memos, correspondence, notes and other material on topics relating to migrant farm workers, including education, farm labor, and health (47 folders), 1978-1981 (Box 345)
    - Sacramento Migrant Unit, correspondence, 1981 (Boxes 341-342)
  - Series 4. Training Programs
    - Attorney conferences; includes correspondence, memos, notes, meeting agendas and related material; also directing attorney orientation material (10 folders), 1978-1988 (Box 314)
    - Attorney and staff training; includes materials related to LSC and budget training; new attorney orientation material; conferences, articles, other training programs and continuing education (39 folders), circa 1973-1982 (Carton 51)
    - Training and orientation; includes memos, correspondence, agendas, and conference materials related to training for CRLA attorneys, community workers, and office staff (30 folders), 1979-1981 (Carton 134)
    - Training and orientation; includes memos, correspondence, agendas, and conference materials related to training for CRLA attorneys, community workers, and office staff (22 folders), 1977-1979 (Carton 133)
    - Trial advocacy course; correspondence, notes, and training material; also clerical and legal writing training material (9 folders), 1983-1986 (Box 315)
  - Series 5. Miscellaneous Program Files
    - Education programs (Stephen Rosenbaum files); education training and task force materials, mostly related to migrant and bilingual education; includes memos, correspondence, reports, clippings, pleadings (26 folders), circa 1980-1984 (Carton 33)
    - Education programs (Stephen Rosenbaum files); education training and task force materials, mostly related to migrant and bilingual education; includes memos, correspondence, reports, clippings, pleadings (13 folders), circa 1980-1984 (Box 34)
    - Immigration programs; includes correspondence, memos, research, testimony, newsletters, reports, and other materials relating to the CRLA's immigration program; especially material relating to the Select Commission on Immigration and Refugee Policy (21 folders), 1979-1981 (Carton 69)
    - Mixed conference and meeting files; includes migrant and priorities conference files; regional office meeting reports; related publications (11 folders), 1983-1986 (Box 316)
    - Political rights programs; includes notes, correspondence, memos, pleadings, reports, and other materials relating to political rights in California (33 folders), circa 1973 (Carton 352)
    - Prison aid records; includes notes, correspondence, memos, and other materials relating to efforts by CRLA to assist California prisoners with legal issues, 1971-1972 (Cartons 348-349)
      Closed until 2047
    - Reclamation and immigration programs; includes correspondence, memos, research, testimony, statistics, reports, and other materials relating to the CRLA’s immigration and reclamation programs; especially material relating to the Select Commission on Immigration and Refugee Policy (30 folders), 1977-1981 (Carton 68)
    - Reclamation Unit; includes notes, correspondence, memos, and pleadings relating to litigation over the status of reclaimed lands; cases include U.S. v. Tulare Lake Canal Co., United Family Farmers v. Kleppe, and Yellen v. Hickel/Andrus (17 folders), circa 1972 (Carton 347)
    - San Diego project; materials relating to the opening of a migrant services office in the San Diego area and reallocating resources from the Salinas office; includes memos, correspondence, reports, clippings, circa 1987-1989 (Box 30)
- Record Group 7. Audiovisual material, circa 1978-1993
  This record group contains video tapes and audio tapes of programs featuring CRLA staff, such as hearings and conference recordings, as well as telecasts on topics of interest to CRLA.
  Arrangement
  Some of the material in this record group was removed from other record groups. Separated material notes, which describe the original location of the item, have been added when relevant. Documentation that accompanied these items has also been retained in this record group.
  - Priorities Conference at Asilomar (6 videotapes and documentation), 1979 (Box 121)
  - Videotapes (18) of news coverage on issues of concern to CRLA, such as mechanization and immigration, 1978-1981 (Carton 122)
  - Videotapes (14) of news coverage on issues of concern to CRLA, including farm mechanization and pesticides; also La Voz del Pueblo, a public service announcement produced by CRLA in English and Spanish, and two folders of documentation, 1978-1980, 1984 (Carton 123)
  - Cannery Closure Hearings (3 audiocassettes and documentation), 1980 (Half-box 370)
    Separated Materials
    Removed from Record Group 6, Box 345
  - Unlabeled audiocassette (Half-box 370)
  - Zambrano v. INS; Derechos Lopez para arrestados por INS (audiocassette) (Half-box 370)
    Removed from Record Group 5, Carton 228
  - Unlabeled audiocassette (Rosenbaum papers) (Half-box 370)
    Removed from Record Group 5 Box 368
  - Angelina Vasquez-Valdivia (audiocassette) (Half-box 370)
    Removed from Record Group 5 Box 182
- Record Group 8. Government Relations, circa 1966-2000
  This record group contains memos, correspondence, reports, news clippings, and statistics concerning CRLA's relationships with various federal, state, and local government agencies. The Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO), later the Legal Services Corporation (LSC), is CRLA's main source of funding and this relationship is well documented in this record group, which includes extensive material related to LSC monitoring and audits of CRLA. Ronald Reagan's investigation of CRLA activities and his efforts to defund CRLA, particularly his 1970 veto, are also well documented.
  - Series 1. Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) and Legal Services Corporation (LSC)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO); includes applications, proposals, refunding hearing transcripts and closing memorandum (9 folders), 1966-1973 (Box 7)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) refunding proposals; includes appendices, applications, proposals, and support letters for Office of Economic Opportunity refunding of CRLA (25 folders), 1967, 1971, 1973-1975 (Carton 135)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO); includes correspondence, reports, and memos relating to CRLA evaluation of other OEO-funded legal aid groups, refunding, revenue sharing, and other topics. (10 folders), 1969-1975 (Box 80)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO); includes Community Action Program (CAP) memos; mostly information on funding (5 folders), 1966-1971 (Box 39)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO); includes manuals and guidelines relating to the OEO's Community Action Program (CAP), grant applications and instructions, newsclippings, and material on Judicare and CRLA's Senior Citizens Project (22 folders), 1965, 1967-71 (Carton 155)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) and Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes an application for refunding to the OEO and material relating to LSC monitoring visits in 1985 and 1987 (44 folders), 1971, 1985, 1987 (Carton 157)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) and Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes correspondence, memos, lists, notes, and other materials relating to the debate over OEO's defunding and the legislative defeat of the LSC. (12 folders), 1973-1974 (Box 90)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) and Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes newsclippings and memoranda related to Reagan's veto of funding for CRLA in 1971, refunding applications, evaluations, and travel reimbursement (15 folders), 1971, 1973-74, 1980 (Carton 158)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes correspondence, memos, budgets and other materials documenting CRLA's relationship with the LSC; topics include the Project Advisory Group and its Funding Criteria Committee (5 folders), 1975-1977 (Box 82)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes correspondence, memos, budgets, and other material documenting CRLA's relationship with the LSC (14 folders), 1975-1978 (Carton 81)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes memos, correspondence, reports, and grant applications related to the Legal Services Corporation (LSC); topics include mergers of smaller legal aid associations with CRLA, as well as Congressional debates over appropriations for LSC (28 folders), 1975-1980 (Carton 60)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes memos, correspondence, grant applications, and reports related to the LSC; topics include programs for special needs clients (18 folders), 1978-1981 (Carton 71)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes memos, correspondence, reports, grant applications, and audits related to the Legal Services Corporation (LSC); topics include training seminars, restrictions on the use of funds to aid non-resident aliens, and lobbying restrictions (25 folders), 1980-1984 (Carton 61)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes memos, correspondence, grant applications, and reports related to the LSC (18 folders), 1981-1985 (Carton 72)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes memos, correspondence, news clippings, and applications related to monitorings and refunding (15 folders), 1985-88, 1990 (Carton 96)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes regulations from the Legal Services Corporation Act of 1974 and the Amended Act of 1977, analysis and correspondence relavant to regulations, also includes ethical duties under the regulations, relavant case summaries (19 folders), 1976-1990 (Carton 220)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC), funding battle; includes legislative updates, news clippings, memos, alternative budget planning (26 folders), 1981 (Carton 54)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes correspondence, reports, newsletters, memos, and other material related to LSC's activities; subjects include LSC appropriations for FY 1981, budget materials, information on social cutbacks, support letters, Cesar Chavez and the UFW, block grants to state legislatures, cutback management, and private bar involvement (16 folders) (Carton 136)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes budgets, evaluations, reports, regulations, and grant conditions for LSC programs (17 folders), 1977-1985 (Carton 204, Folders 1-17)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes refunding applications and related notes and correspondence (14 folders), 1985-1987 (Carton 365)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes grant applications, monitoring reports, and related material (8 folders), 1988 (Box 190)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes grant applications, monitoring reports, and related material (19 folders), 1989-1991 (Carton 169)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); includes material related to LSC grant applications; ULWC contract information; IOLTA applications; also Private Attorney Involvement (PAI) program materials (7 folders), 1987-1991 (Box 191)